<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<doc name="cat_health.xml">
  <block>
    <block>Signs of a Healthy Cat</block>
    <block>Do you know how to tell if your cat is healthy? Healthy cat food with the proper nutrition can play an important role in the well-being of your cat, but that’s only one influential component in overall cat health. Your veterinarian can help you with check-ups and whenever there is something specific you’re concerned about with your cat, but here is a checklist to help you get an overall picture of your cat’s health:</block>
    <block>Digestive Health</block>
    <block>Keep an eye on your cat’s litter box: stools should be small and firm. That’s a sign that your cat is retaining the nutrition from his or her food. Your cat should also be comfortable using the litter box and not going to the bathroom outside of it. If your cat is avoiding the litter box, speak to your veterinarian. Additionally, if you want to support a healthy digestive system, you may want to consider feeding her cat food for sensitive stomachs.</block>
    <block>Eyes</block>
    <block>Healthy cats have eyes that are bright and clear. Discharge around their eyes or cloudy pupils could be a symptom of any number of larger issues, so don’t hesitate to ask your veterinarian about it.</block>
    <block>Skin and Coat</block>
    <block>Your cat’s skin and coat are vitally important to his or her overall health. Dry skin on cats can often indicate a problem, as can lack of grooming. A healthy cat has smooth hair that’s rich in color and free of flakes and mats.</block>
    <block>Healthy Energy</block>
    <block>Is your cat playful? Does he or she spend a lot of time being active? If your cat has healthy energy, that’s a great indicator of good overall health.</block>
    <block>Clean Teeth</block>
    <block>Healthy cat teeth are free of tartar and plaque. You can tell if your cat is developing either of these by looking at his or her back teeth – there shouldn’t be any unusual yellowing or darkening back there. Your cat’s gums should be a bright pink, and your cat’s breath shouldn’t be too offensive.</block>
  </block>
</doc>
