<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<doc name="drink_milk_alternative.xml">
  <block>
    <block>The rising demand for alternatives</block>
    <block>While there’s a lot of research looking at the effects of cow’s milk on our health, there’s less research for dairy-free alternatives. A glance at any supermarket’s milk aisle suggests rising demand for these alternatives, made with soy, almonds, cashews, hazelnuts, coconuts, macadamia nuts, rice, flax, oats or hemp. The main ingredient is processed and diluted with water and other ingredients, including stabilisers such as gellan gum and locust bean gum.</block>
    <block>Soya milk is the best replacement for cow’s milk in terms of protein, as it’s the only one with comparable protein content. But the proteins in alternative drinks may not be “true” protein, says Givens.</block>
    <block>“It may be of a substantially lower quality protein than milk, which is a critical point for children and the elderly in particular, who have an absolute requirement for high quality protein for bone development,” he says.</block>
    <block>There’s no research to suggest we can get much nutrition from the main ingredients in these drinks, says Sina Gallo, a nutrition scientist from George Mason University's department of nutrition and food studies in Virginia, US. They may contain other micronutrients, she adds, but you won’t get the same benefits from an almond drink as you would from eating almonds.</block>
    <block>Milk alternatives are usually fortified with the nutrients that occur naturally in cow’s milk, such as calcium. But scientists don’t know if fortified vitamins and minerals give us the same health benefits as those naturally occurring in cow’s milk and say further research is needed to establish the consequences of added calcium in the human body.</block>
    <block>“The bioavailability of calcium may be different when it’s fortified compared to when found naturally, and this is a big issue with some of these products,” says Gallo. “Cow’s milk contains other things, including fat, which may affect nutrients’ bioavailability.”</block>
    <block>In the US, however, cow’s milk is fortified with vitamin D, and research suggests this can have similar beneficial effects to getting the vitamin naturally from sun exposure.</block>
    <block>Nevertheless, experts are advising that we don’t assume that these alternatives are a like-for-like for children, says nutritionist Charlotte Stirling-Reed – even when they are fortified. “Cow’s milk is a very nutrient-dense food, and fortified plant milk doesn’t always cover all nutrients,” she says.</block>
    <block>Stirling-Reed argues that we need public health guidance on whether alternative drinks can be used as a substitute for cow’s milk for children, as well as for the elderly. “Switching children from cow’s milk to other beverages could be a public health issue, but we just don’t have a lot of research for it yet.”</block>
    <block>There are also concerns about what milk alternatives do contain, as well as what they lack. While cow’s milk contains lactose, a naturally occurring sugar, milk alternatives often contain added sugar, which is more harmful to our health.</block>
    <block>Deciding whether to drink cow’s milk or one of the many alternatives can be confusing – partly because there are so many options. Picking your go-to milk or milk alternative isn’t a question of what’s deemed unhealthy or healthy, says Hernandez, but looking at the nutritional information of each and deciding which drink is best for you individually.</block>
    <block>Someone who isn’t lactose intolerant, who is at high risk of developing osteoporosis or heart disease, for example, might choose low-fat cow’s milk, while someone who’s concerned about the environment might choose the one with the lowest environmental cost.</block>
    <block>“You can decide which drink suits you, and continue to refine your diet and make the right decisions for your context,” says Gardner.</block>
    <block>Whatever you decide, you won’t necessarily be missing out on vital nutrients if you eat a balanced diet. In most cases, a substitute, or substitutes, can be used in place of milk. “While it’s not necessary to avoid milk, it’s also not necessary that we drink milk, either,” says Virtanen. “It can be replaced with other products – there’s no single dietary component or food that’s absolutely necessary to our health.”</block>
  </block>
</doc>
