<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<doc name="drink_cow_milk.xml">
  <block>
    <block>Milk plays a crucial role in the life of all mammals, right from birth. But some say that drinking another mammal’s milk is unnecessary, unnatural, even unhealthy.</block>
    <block>As the only animal to drink the milk of another species, humans have an unusual relationship with the white stuff. Most other animals are weaned off milk in infancy, once we start to need more complex foods. So why do humans keep drinking it?</block>
    <block>People living in parts of the world where cows were domesticated – starting in south-west Asia and spreading into Europe – only evolved to digest lactose around 10,000 years ago. As a result, around 30% of the world’s population continue to produce lactase, the enzyme required to be able to digest lactose, into adulthood. The rest cut back their production after the weaning phase of infancy.</block>
    <block>Most people, then, become lactose intolerant, making milk-drinking Europeans, along with some African, Middle Eastern and Southern Asian populations, the exception rather than the rule. Among people of European descent in the US, only around 9% are lactose intolerant. Even those who can digest it might wish to reduce their milk intake because of other concerns, such as our health and the environmental costs of animal agriculture, which has been driving the growth of dairy-free alternatives to cow’s milk. (Read more about which humans evolved to drink milk, and why).</block>
    <block>But are there any health benefits to ditching cow’s milk for an alternative drink, or does cow’s milk provide us with vital nutrients we can’t get elsewhere? And does milk actually aggravate most people’s lactose intolerance?</block>
    <block>Cow’s milk is a good source of protein and calcium, as well as nutrients including vitamin B12 and iodine. It also contains magnesium, which is important for bone development and muscle function, and whey and casein, which have been found to play a role in lowering blood pressure.</block>
    <block>The UK’s National Health Service recommends children between the age of one and three consume 350 milligrams of calcium a day, which just over half a pint of milk would provide, for healthy bone development. But when it comes to adults, research as to whether cow’s milk helps to keep our bones healthy is conflicting.</block>
    <block>While calcium is required for healthy bones, the evidence that consuming a calcium-rich diet will prevent bone fractures is unclear. A number of studies have found no significant decrease in fracture risk from drinking milk, while some research suggests that milk could actually contribute to fracture risk.</block>
    <block>One study in Sweden found that women who drank more than 200 millilitres of milk daily – less than one glass – had a higher risk of fractures. However, the study was observational, so the researchers cautioned against hyperbolic interpretations of their findings. It could be that people who are prone to fractures tend to drink more milk, warns the study’s author.</block>
    <block>But calcium is crucial during our adolescence for the development of bone strength, says Ian Givens, an expert in food chain nutrition at the University of Reading.</block>
    <block>“If you don’t get bone development correct in your teenage years, you run a higher risk of bone weakness in later life, particularly for women after the menopause, who lose the benefits of oestrogen,” Givens says. (Read more about whether we should drink milk to strengthen bones).</block>
  </block>
  <block>
    <block>Health concerns</block>
    <block>Another concern around milk in recent decades is the hormones we consume in cow’s milk. Cows are milked when they’re pregnant, when their oestrogen levels increase 20-fold. Although one study linked these oestrogen levels to breast, ovarian and uterine cancers, Laura Hernandez, who studies lactation biology at the University of Wisconsin in the US, says ingesting hormones through cow’s milk is nothing to worry about. After all, “Human milk has hormones in it, too – it’s part of being a mammal,” she says.</block>
    <block>A more recent review of studies looking into whether the amount of oestrogen consumed via milk is harmful found no cause for concern. Researchers found that oestrogen levels only start to affect mice’s reproductive systems when supplemented with 100 times the levels found in cow’s milk, and researchers only detected an increase in oestrogen levels in female mice and a decrease in testosterone levels in male mice after the dosage reached 1,000 times normal levels. It’s very unlikely that humans are a thousand times more sensitive to oestrogen levels in milk than mice, says the study’s author, Gregor Majdic, a researcher at the University of Ljubljana's Center for Animal Genomics in Slovenia.</block>
    <block>Studies have also found a link between milk intake and heart disease, due to milk’s saturated fat content. But whole milk only contains around 3.5% fat, semi-skimmed around 1.5% and skimmed milk 0.3% – while unsweetened soya, almond, hemp, coconut, oat and rice drinks have lower levels of fat than whole milk. (Read more about the true risks of saturated fats.)</block>
    <block>In one study, researchers divided participants into four groups based on the amount of milk they drank, but they found that only those who drank the most – almost one litre per day – had an increased risk of heart disease. The association could be because those who drink so much milk don’t have a healthy diet, says Jyrkia Virtanen, a nutritional epidemiologist at the University of Eastern Finland.</block>
    <block>“Only very high milk intake can be bad, but there’s no research suggesting that moderate intake is harmful,” he says.</block>
    <block>It’s also possible that those with lactose intolerance may be able to drink small amounts of cow’s milk. Some experts argue that adverse symptoms – such as bloating and stomach cramps – are a response to a build-up of lactose in the body, and each individual has a different threshold before experiencing symptoms.</block>
    <block>Christopher Gardner, a nutrition scientist at Stanford Prevention Research Center in California, carried out a study comparing the symptoms of people with lactose intolerance when they drank two cups of soya milk, raw milk or regular milk every day. He found that many of them didn’t experience serious symptoms.</block>
    <block>“We found lactose intolerance is less of a dichotomy than a continuum, and that a lot of people can tolerate modest amounts of dairy,” he says.</block>
  </block>
</doc>
