<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<doc name="plane_in_lockdown.xml">
  <block>
    <block>Man builds, flies plane in lockdown</block>
    <block>Wellington writer Craig Gamble on the joys and despairs of building model aircraft.</block>
    <block>I’m building an aeroplane off a plan I downloaded from the internet, and using scraps of leftover balsa wood from a previous kit. I’m lucky to have two thirds of a bottle of glue, stored at the back of the fridge for months. Thin CA (cyanoacrylate) glue works like a miniature welding gun on balsa, fusing pieces instantly and often emitting a puff of astringent fumes in the process. The glue soaks in fast and runs along the grain, making it very easy to glue your fingers to the wood or to each other. Skin soaks up CA like a sponge. But the glued joints are very strong, and if you have the pieces in place, you can move along the frame of a wing or fuselage quickly.</block>
    <block>I first started building model aeroplanes when I was about 10. They were mostly plastic kitsets, replicas of famous aircraft from WWI and WWII – Spitfires, Camels, a Sunderland Flying Boat, the Focke-Wulf 190. I was obsessed with flying and dreamt of entering the Air Force, a path blocked by my poor mathematical brain (pilot trainees needed physics) and a brief spell in the Air Training Corps. The Corps was like the Scouts, but with less camping and a higher ratio of teenagers who thought they were drill sergeants. As the years went on I gathered equipment to take my model building to a higher level. I wanted to make the photo-realistic aircraft I saw in modelling magazines, set in detailed dioramas with lounging pilots smoking cigarettes and beautifully rendered grass. So I had airbrushes, work boards, trays of scalpels, files and sandpapers, spice racks full of myriad types of glue, fillers and varnishes. More paint than a suburban branch of Resene’s, a collection of books with titles like An Illustrated Guide to Luftwaffe Camouflage: Western Front, 1942. If I couldn’t fly, I could at least live inside aeroplanes.</block>
    <block>But the reality rarely rose above a clear canopy smeared with glue, a fingerprint in an otherwise competent paint scheme. Nicholson Baker sums it up in his essay Model Aeroplanes (from The Size of Thoughts) – "the activity of model construction goes to its final rest in one’s memory as a long, gradual disappointment." The kitsets were never more perfect than when they were nestled in their gaudily illustrated boxes, their parts untouched by glue, unsullied by poor painting technique or the misapplied decal. "Straight from the store, these kits are museums," says Baker. "Kremlins and Smithsonian’s of the exploded view." All my plastic builds were failures in one way or another, or lived only briefly in their finished state before being repurposed as something else.</block>
    <block>Building a kit as an adult is a different activity; less about Biggles, more about the slow accumulation of progress. I’m no longer obsessed with perfection, happy to get to a level that feels satisfying enough. Happy to be doing something with my hands that occupies the part of my brain that would otherwise worry at some pointless thing. This is never more true than now. Under lockdown, even small setbacks can suddenly balloon into a mini-crisis. Going to the supermarket is beset with anxieties: have I got enough food, have I chosen the right things, is someone here sick. There’s the feeling that everyone is watching you whenever you leave the house, wary of what you might be carrying or what you might do. The waves and hellos I get out running are often strained, an anxious mix of "we’re all in this together" and "please keep your distance".</block>
    <block>But model building is just the right level of mental and physical occupation to push those worries down. These days all my builds are in balsa wood, which is a different skill set – slower and more time greedy. There’s a lot of careful cutting and sanding to get the parts ready to assemble. And once you start putting it all together, pinning and cementing the pieces in place, there’s no escaping the fact that you are working on a replica. Unlike plastic, a balsa kit is not a literal imitation of the real thing, though sometimes its construction is eerily realistic. It has its own rules. And now I stop building one step before the finish, the balsa frames of the wings and fuselage uncovered with tissue or plastic, displaying the intricate skeleton of wood, delicate and endlessly adaptable into any complex shape.</block>
    <block>Another of my lockdown jags has been rewatching all the Studio Ghibli movies where flying machines have a major role – Porco Rosso, The Wind Rises, Kiki’s Delivery Service. What really appeals to me is the way the aircraft (and the cars and buses and other vehicles too) are drawn. They are both forensically accurate and realistically animated – they move like the vehicles should move (even the cat bus in My Neighbor Totoro flies in a way that seems completely right for its twelve paws and accommodatingly hollow body). My favourite scenes are in The Wind Rises, where the main character Jiro Horikoshi is at his drawing board, draughting up his newest aircraft. Suddenly he is airborne, the machine assembling itself all around him, the wind lifting his hair and clothes in a whirl of slipstream and flight, before gently depositing him back at his desk.</block>
    <block>Lockdown itself mockingly imitates many of the characteristics of long-distance flying. The same glut of movies to catch up on, the same anticipation of the next meal, and the next, if only to mark time. The feeling that your street is shrinking to the width of an aisle in a 747. Building a balsa wood plane isn’t flying either, but like a Ghibli movie, it both unshackles me from the anxieties of the current mess and gives me access to a place where it’s OK to daydream about things more insubstantial. It’s a good way to travel.</block>
  </block>
</doc>
