<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<doc name="professor_under_fire.xml">
  <block>
    <block>The professor under fire</block>
    <block>By Carter Dougherty</block>
    <block>HEIDELBERG, Germany — With his lengthy digressions about the peculiarities of German tax law, Paul Kirchhof can sound a little professorial on the campaign trail, a quality now under heavy fire in a closely fought campaign for the federal elections Sunday.</block>
    <block>Stumping for votes before a friendly crowd of over 500 in the heart of the city where he teaches law, Kirchhof, the academic who is the conservatives' candidate to become finance minister if they win on Sunday, dwelt on the minutiae of taxation as he advanced plans to overhaul the notoriously complex system.</block>
    <block>Kirchhof took pains to defend himself against charges that conservative plans are cold-hearted: The secretary will not pay more in taxes than her millionaire boss, he stressed. But with red-shirted members of the Social Democrats' youth organization just outside the building taunting Kirchhof to "tell the truth," he left the impression of being vulnerable, even while fighting for his beliefs.</block>
    <block>"I knew I was walking into an arena where the tone is shrill," Kirchhof said. "I didn't realize there would be so much wrong information."</block>
    <block>The saga of Kirchhof's entry into the campaign and the controversial position he now occupies reinforces the adage about just how much can change in a few weeks of intense politics.</block>
    <block>To much applause from the media and experts last month, Angela Merkel, the conservative Christian Democrats' candidate to lead Germany, drafted Kirchhof to spearhead a reformist message and build a can-do image.</block>
    <block>With 12 years as a judge on Germany's highest court behind him and now a professor in Heidelberg, Kirchhof burnished Merkel's campaign.</block>
    <block>Now, with the election on Sunday appearing an ever-tighter race against the Social Democrats of Chancellor Gerhard Schröder, Kirchhof's appointment dogs Merkel at every step.</block>
    <block>Questions about what Kirchhof represents - his own radical ideas or the conservative party's mellower stance in its program - have obscured the conservatives' message. Schröder's camp has found a powerful tool to attract the attention of voters - with a fifth of them still undecided. And Merkel is forced to defend Kirchhof because to drop him now would send a message of weakness.</block>
    <block>The latest polling suggests that the Christian Democrats, who a month ago were being forecast to win a sizable majority along with their prospective coalition partners, the business-friendly Free Democrats, might not get the votes needed to form a government. This has raises the prospect of a "grand coalition" with the Social Democrats, an eventuality viewed with dread all around.</block>
    <block>The firestorm around Kirchhof has become so great that some Christian Democrats are now dangling the name of Friedrich Merz, an accomplished financial policy expert who fell out with Merkel last year, as someone who should play an important role alongside Kirchhof. Merz has largely faded into the background during the campaign.</block>
    <block>With jeering references to "the professor from Heidelberg" who wants to make Germany his "guinea pig," Schröder has deftly used Kirchhof's reputation to exploit a crucial advantage for the left in Germany: the many citizens who say radical reform is needed, but get queasy when it actually looms.</block>
    <block>"There's the old German saying, 'Wash my fur, but don't get me wet,'" said Norbert Walter, chief economist for Deutsche Bank. "Well, guess what: When you wash somebody down, he gets wet."</block>
    <block>Officially, Kirchhof is pushing the Christian Democrats' own proposal for a change that will introduce personal tax rates ranging from 12 to 39 percent and a corporate rate of 22 percent. But Kirchhof built his reputation as a reformer with his personal, and much more radical, plan whose signature element is a 25 percent flat tax and a virtual elimination of tax deductions.</block>
    <block>"Merkel wanted to demonstrate a break with the past, but instead she injected uncertainty into the mix," said Uwe Andersen, a political scientist at the University of Bochum. "Is it Kirchhof or the Christian Democrats' program I'm voting for?"</block>
    <block>Even Christian Democratic supporters seem eager for a clear distinction between voting for the party and endorsing Kirchhof's ideas.</block>
    <block>"It sounds simple and good, but you have to make sure it works," said Andreas Winkler, while waiting for Kirchhof to speak.</block>
    <block>Social Democrats have seized on the ambiguity with charges that Kirchhof, who Merkel has said would be her preferred finance minister, would treat rich and poor the same.</block>
    <block>Likewise, charges that Kirchhof would immediately lift an existing exemption from taxes for night and Sunday work resonate with voters, even though the Christian Democrats have not proposed this.</block>
    <block>Schröder's ferocious campaign against Kirchhof raises the question of where the Social Democrats, after seven years in power, now propose to steer the country. But with his departure all but certain - polls put his coalition with the Green party well short of a majority - Schröder has been able to attack, without giving his opponents much to go on.</block>
    <block>"I can't compare myself with nothing," Kirchhof complained.</block>
    <block>Social Democrats say they want to forge ahead with their business-friendly Agenda 2010, although having already lowered unemployment benefits, the program now consists mostly of softer issues, like investment in research and education. Eager to reconcile their own feuding factions, they have also proposed a tax on the rich that plays well on the left but makes Schröder's plans inconsistent at best, Andersen noted.</block>
  </block>
</doc>
