<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<doc name="professor_china_holding.xml">
  <block>
    <block>China Is Said to Be Holding a Professor Based in Japan</block>
    <block>By Jane Perlez</block>
    <block>BEIJING — A Chinese specialist in Sino-Japanese affairs who has been living in Japan appears to have been detained by the Chinese government since late July and is being questioned about his activities, according to Chinese academics and a Japanese newspaper.</block>
    <block>News of the apparent detention comes as relations between China and Japan have hit their lowest point in decades, and has sent tremors of fear through the small communities of Chinese and Japanese academics who live in each other’s countries.</block>
    <block>The Chinese government hinted but declined to confirm that the specialist, Zhu Jianrong, a professor at a university near Tokyo, was in custody after he traveled to his native Shanghai for a meeting July 17.</block>
    <block>In a statement released in September, the Foreign Ministry said: “Zhu Jianrong is a Chinese citizen. China is a country ruled by law, and will protect the legitimate rights and interests of Chinese citizens. While at the same time, all Chinese citizens should abide by the law.”</block>
    <block>The Japan Times recently reported his detention in an editorial on Sept. 29, without citing a source. A group that Mr. Zhu helped found, the Society of Chinese Professors in Japan, said Monday that it was almost certain Mr. Zhu was being held and was “currently responding to questioning.”</block>
    <block>The society described him as “very active” in his role as “a bridge between China and Japan.” He was chairman of the group for nine years, and often appeared on Japanese television discussing the soured relations between the two countries.</block>
    <block>There were some suggestions that Mr. Zhu met with Chinese military officials this year in connection with his research, and that the Chinese authorities were suspicious of his subsequent use of the information.</block>
    <block>The Japan Times editorial said that China was looking into the meetings and whether they constituted an illegal collection of information.</block>
    <block>The editorial also noted that in 2009, a former deputy director of the Institute of Japanese Studies at the Chinese Academy of Sciences, Jin Xide, was imprisoned for 14 years on charges of selling Chinese state secrets to Japan and South Korea. It also reported that Su Ling, chief editor of Xinhua Shibao, a Chinese-language newspaper published in Japan, has been missing since he came to Beijing from Japan in May.</block>
    <block>Willy Lam, adjunct professor at the Chinese University of Hong Kong’s Center for Chinese Studies, said that the Zhu case could further fracture the “quasi-cold-war relationship” between China and Japan, setting off fears among Chinese academics and visitors to Japan that they could be susceptible to similar treatment.</block>
    <block>Noting the other cases, Mr. Lam, who has worked in Japan, said: “These folks are not famous people. Inevitably it will affect people-to-people exchanges, popular diplomacy and people-level diplomacy between the two countries.”</block>
    <block>In his appearances on Japanese TV, Mr. Zhu was resolute in defending China’s case on the bitter dispute over the islands in the East China Sea, known as the Diaoyu islands in China and as the Senkaku islands in Japan. The dispute involves patrols by naval vessels, as well as air sorties, by both China and Japan. China most recently was reported to have sent a drone over the area.</block>
    <block>Mr. Zhu married a Japanese researcher in the 1980s, and moved to Japan in 1986, where he worked at the Toyo Gakuen University.</block>
    <block>The Society of Chinese Professors in Japan expressed concern for Mr. Zhu, saying it hoped he would “return to normal life as soon as possible.” The group praised him for trying to improve the relationship between the two countries.</block>
  </block>
</doc>
